Samuel Hay Kauffmann Family Photographs Collection P001
People's Archive, MLK Library
Samuel Hay Kauffmann Family Photographs Collection
1844-1916
People's Archive, MLK Library
Kauffman, Samuel H.
P001
0.5 Linear feet
1 Boxes
Arrangement
Items were arranged into the following four series; they were arranged chronologically within each series: S.H. Kauffmann; Louise Kauffmann Simpson; Victor Kauffmann; Related Photographs and Papers.
Arrangement
Series 1: S.H. Kauffmann Series 2: Louise Kauffmann Simpson Series 3: Victor Kauffmann Series 4: Related Photographs and Papers
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Hay Kauffmann was born in Wayne County, Ohio on April 30, 1829. Early on he learned the printing trade and became an editor and publisher in Zanesville, Ohio. In 1861 he was appointed to a position in the United States Treasury under Secretary Salmon P. Chase. He purchased an interest in the Washington Evening Star in 1867 and was elected its president in 1868. He was president of the newspaper from 1868-1879 and again from 1886 until his death in February 1906. Samuel Kauffmann and his wife, Sarah, had at least three children, Rudolph, Louise and Victor. Louise married Dr. John Crayke Simpson in 1905 and continued to live in Washington, D.C. until her death in 1930. Rudolph worked for The Star, married and had a family. Victor also worked for The Star as an editor, and with his wife Jessie (Christopher) had two sons, Philip Christopher Kauffmann and Samuel Hay Kauffmann. They in turn grew up to work for The Star.
Custodial History
There is no deed of gift for this collection and it is uncertain how the Library acquired the photographs. The collection was accessioned into the collection in 1975.
Related Materials
DCPL Collections: Washington Star Papers (061) External Collections: Samuel Hay Kauffmann Papers; Library of Congress; control Number mm81028225
Scope and Contents
Approximately 80 photographs of the Kauffmann family including: Samuel Hay Kauffmann, Louise Kauffmann Simpson, Victor Kauffmann, Jessie Christopher Kauffmann, Philip Christopher Kauffmann, and Samuel Hay Kauffmann II. Collection is mostly portrait photographs, including a daguerreotype, tintypes, albumen cartes-de-visite and cabinet cards, gelatin silver developing out paper, and platinum prints. Of note: a tintype Union Case, a Mathew Brady carte-de-visite, Japanese albumen photographic prints with hand coloring, and a hand-written will by S.H. Kauffmann to his wife, Sarah F. Kauffmann dated 1878.
Photographs; Families; Portraits; Prints and Photographs
- Series 1: S.H. Kauffmann portraits
  - Daguerreotype - uncased, ca. 1844-1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    (Glass deteriorating - store glass side down)
  - Tintype in Union Case, ca. 1855 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (Photocopy of Union Case patent info enclosed)
  - Gelatin silver developing out paper print copy of tintype, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cartes-de-visite (4) - albumen, ca. 1862-1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Photographers: Ulke, Brady (Note: c.d.v. by Brady has photocopy of caricature of S.H.K. on verso.)
  - Cartes-de-visite (5) - albumen, ca. 1870-1874 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Photographer: Goldier (sp?)
  - Cartes-de-visite (4) - albumen, ca. 1876 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photographer: M.P. Simons
  - Cabinet cards (4) - albumen, ca. 1876-early 1880s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Photographers; Reichmann, Rice
  - Cabinet cards (4), albumen - ca. early 1880s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Photographer: Rice
  - Cartes-de-visite (4) - albumen, ca. 1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Photographer: Charles Parker
  - Cabinet card - albumen, ca. 1893 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Albumen photo of bas relief profile, ca. 1890s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cabinet card - platinum, ca. 1900-1905 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Platinum print, ca. 1900-1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    (brittle paper)
  - Platinum print, ca. 1900-1905 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    (torn paper, no mount)
  - Platinum print, ca. 1900-1905 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    (from same negative as item 9)
  - Platinum print, ca. 1900-1905 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    (from same sitting as item 9)
- Series 2: Louise Kauffmann Simpson portraits
  - Cartes-de-visite (7) - albumen, ca. 1870-1876 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Photographers: R. Reichmann, Gardner
  - Cabinet cards (4) - albumen, ca. 1872 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Photographer: R.W. Addis
  - Cabinet card - albumen - Western studio scene, ca. 1875 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Photographer: Morse (San Francisco)
  - Cabinet cards (3) - albumen, ca. 1876 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Photographer: R. Reichmann
  - Tintype in paper mat with Mary Chambers, ca. 1876 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Photographer: Johnson's National Gallery
  - Cabinet cards (3) - albumen, ca. 1877 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cabinet cards (3) - albumen, ca. 1880-1889 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Photographers: Rice, Prince
  - Cabinet card with trimmed print with Alma Johnson - albumen, ca. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Photographers: Marceau (S.F.,CA), Jacoby (Minn., MN)
  - Interior of Washington Cottage - Nantucket - Mass. - albumen, ca. 1883 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    broken card mount. Photographer: J. Freeman
  - Cabinet cards (2) - albumen, ca. 1890. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Photographer: C.M. Gilbert
  - Cabinet cards (2 - dup.) - albumen, ca. 1890 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cabinet cards (2 - dup.) - albumen, ca. 1893 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    one with broken card mount,Photographer: C.M. Gilbert
  - Japanese studio print - albumen cabinet card with hand-applied color, ca. 1894 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Photographer: A. Farsari (Yokohama, Japan)
  - Duplicate of item 29, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Japanese studio print - albumen cabinet card with hand-applied color, ca. 1894 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    with Miranda Noyes. Photographer: A. Farsari (Yokohama, Japan)
  - Gelatin silver developing out paper copy photo, ca. 1900 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Portrait - platinum print, ca. 1908 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    print surface damaged - silverfish?
- Series 3: Victor Kauffmann Photographs
  - Cartes-de-visite - albumen - with Mary Downey (Irish servant), ca. 1870 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Photographer: Goldier (sp.?)
  - Cabinet card - albumen, ca. 1886 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Photographer: Geo. Prince
  - Cabinet card - albumen, ca. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Photographer: Pach Bros. (NY)
  - Cartes-de-visite - albumen - with Louise Kauffmann, ca. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Series 4: Related Photographs and Papers
  - Pencil and watercolor caricature of S.H. Kauffmann at easel, ca. late 1880s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Handwritten - signed will from S.H. Kauffmann to wife, November 23 1878 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Philip Christopher Kauffmann (son of Victor and Jessie Christopher Kauffmann; grandson of S.H. Kauffmann) - platinum print, ca. 1901 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    (fragile, torn)
  - Samuel Hay Kauffmann (son of Victor and Jessie Christopher Kauffmann; grandson of S.H. Kauffmann) - platinum print, ca. 1901 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    (extremely fragile, separated into pieces)
  - Jessie Christopher Kauffmann with sons Philip Christopher Kauffmann and Samuel Hay Kauffmann - gelatin printing out paper (?), ca. 1916 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Portrait of unidentified early 19th century man with white hair - possibly painted photograph of original painting or painted paper mounted on board, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    EXTREMELY FRAGILE